I would watch his life on Facebook and
be like this is amazing he traveled the
world he got married he had kids I'm
like am I the idiot and like evidence
was quite possibly Michael quite
possibly this is Alon plus Michael and
today we're going to talk about should
you bootstrap or should you start a VC
backed company this is like a
confusingly controversial topic yeah I'm
not really sure why it's controvers
well it's one of those sort of one-sided
things where a lot of people don't
care about the topic versus people that
care a lot yeah does that make sense and
so I think there's a lot of people that
strongly identify and are really excited
about bootstrapping yeah that are very
like fired up about this and there's a
lot of people that this just isn't a
topic that comes up much yeah the place
we should start I think is that the vast
majority of
businesses um should not raise venture
capital and I'll extend that Point
Venture Capital is not interested in
investing yeah in the vast majority of
businesses so like one of the things I
think Founders get really screwed up on
is that VCS have become a little bit
more
marketingyoutube lot of the stuff that I
see on the television show yeah you
would never in a million years be able
to raise VC from it and so I think you
watch Shark Tank and you think that that
is no reality not this industry so I
think that um that's the first thing is
that if you're starting a business that
can appear on Shark Tank for the most
part you probably shouldn't raise
Venture Capital um but I think there's
actually like a deeper thing here which
is that let's say you want to start a
startup business you don't have to raise
Venture Capital either correct and I'll
say the same thing I don't believe
Venture capitalists want to invest in
all software businesses and I don't
believe all software Founders should
raise Venture Capital yep so yeah let's
talk about the map I think what's really
going on um is I think if you looked at
how many businesses are started every
year yes what percentage of those are
Venture funded Co we could ask chat gbt
but I would guess definitely single
digits if not less than 1% and so if you
just look at businesses that are started
in the world yes it is like a weird
outlier freak occurrence that is a VC
funded business and so but I think if
you're just consuming content you know
you're watching media watching YouTube
Twitter you don't realize that yeah okay
and Venture Capital as a product is
specifically for investing in something
where their investment could be worth at
least a 100 times more if not a thousand
times more yes and so trying to put that
jet fuel into something that um isn't
going to grow to be big everyone is
going to be sad and lose yeah and so you
shouldn't do it and the investor win and
the user no one no one wins no one wins
and so again like I don't think that
there's this push that I can see from
from investors to try to convince people
to raise VC money um for something that
is not has like no chance of of growing
like that it just doesn't make sense for
anybody okay I'll go a step further I
think the whole argument is fake news
right I don't think this is a a real
argument right I don't think that anyone
thinks it's more moral or good or right
to start a VC pack company or a non-vc
pack company I don't think this is an
actual debate yeah I think that like
starting a VCB company really hard not
the best way to get rich not the best
way relatively small number like the
numbers are not huge not a good path
like I always like to equate it to like
Athletics it's like getting into the NBA
is really hard like not like the best
path to have a good career is to be like
oh I'll just I'll just make the NBA yeah
that's simple right it's like 4 or 50
guys I'll just be one of those guys and
then game on right right they recruit
from all around the world I live in the
world yeah very straightforward I like
that play yeah no so it's this is not
the only way to get rich Let's Take a
further step most people who are rich
did not raise Venture Capital dollars
did not start real estate investing
stock market investing being lawyers
being doctors again go num investors
yeah there's so many people right so
this is not we get rich I think the
other thing that's funny is like there
is no one trying to force you or cadol
you into starting a VC backed company
like if you don't want to do it don't
don't do it correct it's also a decision
that you can revisit if you don't want
to start a VCB company now but like your
bootstrap product starts doing well and
you want to do it in the future great
you can there's no one who is going to
say no you said you were bootstrapped on
Twitter I will not give you money like
no I'll get another truth empirically
none of the trillion dollar software
companies um are bootstrapped with no VC
dollars ever yeah so if you if someone's
telling you you can make a trillion
dollar company maybe you can just no
one's ever done it yeah I'll say fact
based and again like to look at the
numbers even if you look at software
companies yeah even if you look at
iPhone apps if you actually did an audit
of the App Store and you said what
percentage of the apps in the App Store
are VC backed it is Tiny tin but if you
said what percentage of dollars that are
spent in mobile apps go into VC backed
companies I think that that's right
because dollars are going into Amazon
and eBay and like all that kind of stuff
right yes and by the way I don't I want
to be clear neither of us are saying you
should want to make one of those
companies yes like or you that should
come from inside of you not from YouTube
no no right like I actually kind of try
to convince people not do it well if it
is because if you need to be talked into
it that's a bad bad so I like to talk
about why it sucks yeah so um I think
the other thing is that no one is trying
to say in our industry that if you make
a great software product that allows you
to make enough money to live a good life
and it's not PC back that you haven't
won you won yep like I had a friend who
made one of these companies um you might
have used his product his product
generated about $30 to $50,000 a month
and took about 7 to 10 hours a month of
Maintenance the entire time I was
working on my startup he was living life
like I would watch his life on Facebook
and be like this is amazing he traveled
the world he got married he had kids I'm
like he won like that's like like good
for him like there's no again this is
the one-sided thing is that we're like
great like we're like high-fiving that
versus that there's this um two-sided
battle 97% of the time I was watching
that Facebook I was like am I the idiot
and like evidence
was quite possibly possibly yes um and
he's still doing great right and so like
this is really clear it's like building
a great small business software small
soft even the term small bothers people
it's just non-venture back non it could
be big non Venture back you making
millions and millions of dollars yes
totally fine I think the other thing
that's kind of maybe a dirt dirty kind
of underbelly here is who is spurning
this argument like who who is who who's
incentivized for this to be a big issue
yeah think that this has been just like
a topic that gets a lot of Engagement
online yeah and so yeah you know if you
want to get people agitated about
something this is a pretty good topic
and then you can use it to
promote stuff and so yeah I'm not going
of name any names but I can think of
folks over the years yeah that are like
kind of um built a following around
encouraging people to do this and to the
extent it is helpful and more people are
improving their lives it that's great
yes but there's a little bit of like
creating a fake controversy and then and
then monetizing it little bit and so
maybe maybe people may have this
question watching this video Michael why
should I apply to YC like why should I
do a v you guys just did a great job of
explaining why not to do it well why why
should I do Venture so I think that um
there are some businesses where you
actually need money
upfront yes and if you you need money up
front and you're building a software
business The Venture Capital industry
can help you get money up front if you
don't need it they'll take it yes I
think that what's so interesting about
this is that um there aren't many other
good mechanisms if you need millions of
dollars or 10 million dollars to get
your company to break even yeah there
aren't other mechanisms in our economy
to give that to you if bu an example of
Google I don't know just cuz famous B
companies the world you know I don't
know how you could have bootstrapped
that and so again maybe the audience is
saying well I don't want to build Google
great you no one is saying you have to
build Google but if Google wants to
build Google but if the founders of
Google wanted to build Google yeah it
doesn't seem mathematically possible
there's no route they could have done it
without raising money there's no loans
they could have gotten to buy the
servers and do the things they did no no
and so we should just be thinking about
VC as enabling incremental
entrepreneurship that wouldn't to be
around otherwise yep not as
cannibalizing anything like it's just
enabling that incremental founder and
the other thing is you have to
remember if you want to raise a lot of
money but you can't explain to the
investor why you might IPO and give them
a lot of money
back then you you can't raise VC we want
to be explicit like it is a business
transaction it's not a faith transaction
correct it it is I give you money now
you give me a lot more money later or at
least you try really hard to and if you
can try really hard but the result can't
be a lot of money I shouldn't logically
give you money now not because I don't
like you or because yeah you're not a
great person or these users you're
trying to serve aren't great it's just
because it's not a good business
transaction it's literally nothing
personal and I think sometimes Founders
kind of are very confused when VC say no
well it's because again if we're we're
trying to stoke outrage you let's Stoke
some outrage you point at something
silly that raised a lot of money yes the
most extreme silly thing in the world
you always pointed youo that' be one
right or we were whatever like you point
to something that is like on face silly
and then you say well if they funded
that why won't they fund my social
network for dogs yes and so it causes a
lot of emotions
yeah um and I understand I relate but
it's don't fall for the rage pillar
don't let yourself get enraged by
obvious engagement bait yes which is to
cherry-pick the craziest silliest thing
yes and use that to get all worked up
and take that personally like that
somehow hurt you like like you were hurt
by that thing over there happening well
and what's so funny is like you are
actually cluded on the real Troop real
truth which is that they screwed up
someone someone messed up like you're
right they shouldn't got there that
money like you you you nailed it that
person who funded that company is an
idiot you're exactly right but like hey
that doesn't mean we should all bets are
all yeah it's like okay this dumb thing
happened therefore Up Is Down black like
like forget everything we know those are
those that doesn't follow that logic
doesn't make sense that person should
probably be uh spoken to about their
investment strategy so yeah so just
understand that game and I have to be
honest like I like games like this like
I don't like games where you have to
like convince people to like you or to
align with your views those are games
that are way harder to play I like games
where it's like hey if I want to serve
this customer and you can be a good
legal partner to me and I I give you
money and you give me Legal Services you
can be a good funding partner for me I
give you a check of my company you give
me cash right if you can be a good
partner to me a simple to understand
partner to me so that I can spend my
time working my
customer that's what I want yeah the
customer complicated
enough Jesus customers complicated
enough I like the idea that the money
people are like so if I give you this
money maybe give me a lot of money back
yes yes okay okay we're good okay
all right end of conversation I give you
money you don't give me any money back
no no
good come back when I come back when
this is all that way
hopefully this helps clear up the debate
but I secretly hope this like I don't
know like doesn't at all cuz this this
is like so silly uh I hope we get
somehow flame word for this anyways
great good chat love it okay sounds good
thanks
[Music]